<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-04T20:03:28+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Geospatial Data Science Group</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">New Job Opportunities at the GDSG, University of Glasgow</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/job-opportunities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Job Opportunities at the GDSG, University of Glasgow"/><published>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/job-opportunities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/job-opportunities/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/logos/job_opp.png" alt="opportunities" width="100%"/></p> <p>We are pleased to announce several new job openings at the University of Glasgow, within the College of Science &amp; Engineering, School of Geographical &amp; Earth Sciences. Available positions include:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Project Manager</strong></li> <li><strong>Administrative Assistant</strong></li> <li><strong>Geospatial AI Research Scientist</strong></li> <li><strong>Research Software Engineer (Geo-AI)</strong></li> <li><strong>Research Associate/Fellow in Urban Analytics</strong></li> <li><strong>Research Associate/Fellow in Statistics of Missing Data</strong></li> <li><strong>Research Associate/Fellow in Agent Based Modelling</strong></li> </ul> <p>All positions are based in Glasgow, with competitive salaries and benefits.</p> <p><strong>Application deadline: 01 October</strong></p> <p>For more details and to apply for the research positions, please visit: <a href="https://www.jobs.ac.uk/search/?keywords=Basiri&amp;location=">jobs.ac.uk</a></p> <p>For more details and to apply for the Administrative Assistant position, please visit: <a href="https://findajob.dwp.gov.uk/details/15173014">jobs.ac.uk</a></p> <p>Also more information on our Opportunities page: <a href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/opportunities/">Opportunities</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Piet Gerrits</name></author><category term="opportunities"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pint Of Science 2024</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/pintofscience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pint Of Science 2024"/><published>2024-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/pintofscience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/pintofscience/"><![CDATA[<p>Join us for a Pint of Science with Dr Ian Turton, Joe Shingleton and Dr Guy Solomon!</p> <p><a href="https://pintofscience.co.uk/event/geospatial-insights">Click here for more information regarding our speakers</a></p> <p><img src="/assets/img/logos/pintofscience.png" alt="Pint of Science" width="100%"/></p> <h3 id="information">Information:</h3> <h4 id="using-ai-to-find-roman-roads">Using AI to find Roman Roads</h4> <p><strong>Dr Ian Turton (Research Software Engineer, University of Glasgow)</strong> Looking at the application of AI to discover the location of Roman roads in the Scottish Borders, the talk will start with a brief explanation of LiDAR data and then show how it can be applied to the discovery of previously unknown Roman roads.</p> <h4 id="geolocation-location-location---how-good-is-ai-at-understanding-spatial-information">(Geo)location, location, location - how good is AI at understanding spatial information?</h4> <p><strong>Joe Shingleton (Research Software Engineer, University of Glasgow)</strong> User-generated, online data is rich with insights into our world. Interpreting the spatial information tying this data to real-world locations is a key challenge. Modern advancements in AI and machine learning might provide a promising solution – but we first need to establish just how well these models really understand spatial information. To answer this, we will explore the ambiguities and complexities of geospatial language, and the limitations of modern AI models.</p> <h4 id="stubborn-minorities-in-cities">“Stubborn” Minorities in Cities</h4> <p><strong>Dr Guy Solomon (Research Associate, University of Glasgow)</strong> It is often assumed that the “majority rules”, but is this actually the case? In many instances, the way a system works is determined by a small, inflexible group (sometimes called a “stubborn minority”) who—for various reasons—may not (or, perhaps, cannot) adapt. This talk outlines what is meant by this term, considers examples of “stubborn minorities” in cities, and discusses why this matters for everyone.</p>]]></content><author><name>Piet Gerrits</name></author><category term="conference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Join us for a Pint of Science with Dr Ian Turton, Joe Shingleton and Dr Guy Solomon!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Defence and Security</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/DSO-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Defence and Security"/><published>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/DSO-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/DSO-video/"><![CDATA[<div class="video-container"> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QB1iz4Syk_k" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Ana Basiri and Joseph Shingleton discuss their work on defence and security. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Petrus Gerrits talks about historical population modelling in Turkey and Bulgaria</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/PG-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Petrus Gerrits talks about historical population modelling in Turkey and Bulgaria"/><published>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/PG-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/PG-video/"><![CDATA[<div class="video-container"> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iOuUdmfqXps" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Petrus Gerrits on historical population modelling. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dominick Sutton on missing data mechanisms</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/DS-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dominick Sutton on missing data mechanisms"/><published>2024-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/DS-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/DS-video/"><![CDATA[<div class="video-container"> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hQiqRb3zSyg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Dominick Sutton talks about how missing data happens. </div> <p>Dominick Sutton is a PhD candidate in the Geospatial Data Science unit. He is researching missing data and how spatial information can be used to improve the accuracy of techniques used to replace the missing values. Missing data is a serious issue for all users of data, including those working in biomedical research, climate change, business, financial and economic analytics. It is a particular problem for users of big data and seriously limits the applicability of their models, not least because it can introduce new forms of data bias that may be especially hard to detect and address.</p> <p>If missing data is present in a dataset it can results in less accurate analysis results and assessment of uncertainty, even if measures are taken to allow for these omissions. This can seriously affect the value of subsequent data uses and limits the value of big data despite its apparent large scale. Prior to undertaking his PhD Dominick was Chief Data Officer of a multinational corporation and before that Chief Economist of a small investment bank. He has Masters’ degrees in Economics, Business Administration and Data Analytics and is a Fellow and Graduate Statistician of the Royal Statistical Society.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Safer End of Engineered Life</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/SEEL-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Safer End of Engineered Life"/><published>2024-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/SEEL-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2024/SEEL-video/"><![CDATA[<div class="video-container"> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nCkBwFPPi_c" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Ana Basiri and Matt Johnston talk about their work in relation to digital inheritance and the climate impact of data. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LBS 2023</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/LBS-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LBS 2023"/><published>2023-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/LBS-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/LBS-2023/"><![CDATA[<p>Attending conferences is one of the most crucial milestones in our academic journey as a PhD student. It means not only gaining knowledge but also following the most up-to-date research in the field, interacting with experienced academics, and getting the opportunity to share our research with a wide range of experts and receive their opinions to improve our research.</p> <p>For the last two years, I have had the chance to attend the ‘Location Based Services’ conference held in Munich in 2022 and in Ghent in 2023. During this time, I had the opportunity to follow the latest developments in location-based services. Thanks to this valuable annual event, we meet the leading names in this field. Organised by Haosheng Huang and Nico Van de Weghe from Ghent University this year, this conference is a meeting point that brings together academics from around the world every year.</p> <p>At the conference, interesting and valuable sessions were held in the ‘Location Based Services’ field, such as ‘LBS and Cycling,’ ‘GeoAI, Urban and Mobility Analytics,’ ‘User Experience, Privacy,’ ‘Innovative LBS Applications,’ ‘User Studies and Data Analysis,’ ‘Wayfinding and Navigation,’ and ‘Positioning and Tracking.’ The sessions offered a broad perspective covering various aspects of this field. In particular, GeoAI sessions attracted attention with the many studies and exciting projects presented in these sessions. GeoAI discusses how artificial intelligence technologies can be used to develop location-based services and innovations in this field. This session became one of the conference’s highlights with its impressive presentations.</p> <p>I had the chance to present our research at this conference. My presentation was titled ‘The Importance of Communication with Missing Data with Colours of Map for Decision-Making.’ In this presentation, I discussed the importance of communication with missing data and how this communication can be perceived through map colours. The valuable suggestions and feedback I received regarding my research will guide me in the further stages of my research.</p> <p>Such events are excellent opportunities for students like me to follow new developments in our field, meet experts, and develop our research further!</p>]]></content><author><name>Merve Polat Kayali</name></author><category term="conference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[attending LBS 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SIGSPATIAL 2023</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/SIGSPATIAL-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SIGSPATIAL 2023"/><published>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/SIGSPATIAL-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/SIGSPATIAL-2023/"><![CDATA[<p>Attending SIGSPATIAL 2023 was an enriching journey! The conference stood at the intersection of GIS, spatial computing, and technological innovation, uniting industry leaders like Alibaba &amp; Google with the forefront of academia.</p> <p>As a PhD student discerning future career paths, I discovered the expansive influence of GIS in areas from risk management to traffic analytics. The Vision Track session was particularly enlightening, showcasing forward-thinking ideas on topics such as open-source mapping, geospatial AI, and spatial data management. These discussions broadened my perspective on the field’s extensive capabilities.</p> <p>Engaging with professionals and peers provided a wealth of knowledge and networking opportunities. The banquet on the last day walked us through SIGSPATIAL’s history, with some of the big names who’ve shaped this conference over the years – absolutely inspiring.</p> <p>I’ve come away with new ideas, valuable connections, and am ready to dive into the future of geospatial computing! Looking forward to SIGSPATIAL 2024 in Atlanta!</p>]]></content><author><name>Xinyi Yuan</name></author><category term="conference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[attending SIGSPATIAL 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the home of the Geospatial Data Science Group at the University of Glasgow</title><link href="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/first-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the home of the Geospatial Data Science Group at the University of Glasgow"/><published>2023-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gdsglasgow.github.io/blog/2023/first-post/"><![CDATA[<p>The Geospatial Data Science Group (GDSG) sits at the intersection between data science and geospatial data. We explore, analyse, model, and infer from geospatial data to design, develop and provide more intelligent and useful location-based services to make smarter, faster, fairer decisions for inclusive societies.</p> <p>The GDSG works towards the process of making sense from geospatial data. We use a wide range of geospatial data, including data from state-of-the-art sensors and ‘new forms of data’ such as crowdsourced and social media data, and develop and implement novel models that can handle data challenges such as uncertainty, bias, missingness, or privacy concerns associated with them to have a better understanding of society, cities and citizens.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guy Solomon</name></author><category term="team"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[about us]]></summary></entry></feed>